so this is a
suitor in the samyut
he goes to the buddha and asks him to
teach and get
to get a teaching and the buddha asks
him some questions
and then gives him instruction
and then melanchia puta responds with
with sort of an in brief to explain that
he
how he understood what it meant
but i want to bring up this verse which
is the same in the bahia
so the buddha asks this monk
what do you think do you have any desire
lust or affection
for those forms cognizable by the eye
that are unseen by you never
seen before that you don't see and that
are not
seen by you now
so do you have any desire or love for
those things that you haven't experienced with
things that you haven't experienced with
your senses
and he replies no
yeah that's like the um
what i said before a number of times
it's like which is more the whole point
of that is
like to to that reflection is to think
do you have lust for things can you have
lost things you haven't seen
like it's inconceivable so having
seen something is a prerequisite for
lust which means lust is not
in seeing not in the sight not in the
side objects
it's basically you responsible for
having lust towards that which is seen
and one of the reasons why people would
have lost or that which is seen is
because they take for granted
that which is seen they take for granted
their sense organs
as as their own as owned
providers of pleasure and so on so then
whatever you see
it's the thing you see you you're fully
centered around that
but if you actually stop and think about
it and doesn't matter what you see
what you have lost the words just kind
of
look at the context of that experience
and see well
okay i've seen this but which is more
things i haven't seen
in my life or things i've seen you
realize the things you've seen are
always going to be inferior to
everything else you haven't seen
everything else your eyes have not
experienced it could be seen
they could be seen but when they are
seen then they become that which is seen
which means there is always going to be
more of that which is not seen
so can you have lust for that which is
not seen that's inconceivable
so the basis for non-last is actually
greater than the basis for lust
and also by thinking like this you
realize then that anything you have seen
was purely circumstantial you realize oh
i could have not seen it
it could have not been it was but it
could have not been so
anything else then with that framework
with that established context
anything else that you see now you see
against that kind of
context of oh it could have not arisen
which means i didn't have saying it's
arising thus you're already much less
much less centered around things you see
much less absorbed in them
which means much less
like narrower basis for the possibility
of lust
because that loss of context and
revolving around that
being being absorbed in seeing her smell
taste touched fully
without any peripheral awareness in
regard to it that is where the lust
breeds and multiplies and grows and expands
and multiplies and grows and expands
so things you've seen are always
secondary to things you haven't seen
they're always circumstantial because
you've seen them
so you realize your lust is always
secondary if you were to cultivate the foundation
if you were to cultivate the foundation
of of
just the recognition of everything that
you haven't seen as a necessary basis
for non-lust
it would be impossible for you to
maintain the loss towards things you are
seeing here and now
so you're recognizing that not yet that
non-desired and
in regard to the immensity of
all the possible things it's all it all
comes down to that practical basically
undermining of that self of that
centeredness upon things you've seen things you heard
upon things you've seen things you heard
things you taste touched and so on
when i say centeredness i mean that
absorption incense objects by default like a
incense objects by default like a
default mode of being
so you want to basically you want to
sort of
start eroding that gratuitous perception
and one of the ways is recognizing that
anything you've seen
anything you will see anything you're
seeing and now
is fundamentally circumstantial because
it's always against the
the the backdrop of everything else not
seen everything else that
that you've never seen and you and and
hasn't been seen
so that kind of puts the current lust
towards things you see
in a better perspective
and also well it also reminds me of the
danger that some lusting after sight or
that some lusting after sight or
experience but this is a circumstance
and how much more experiences are well
how much more experiences are well
that's the thing i'm lasting after
i'm i'm founding my entire being my
entire mental state
all the actions choices they will then
affect me in the future
upon something utterly circumstantial
because if you were to remember that
what you are like currently you're
focused on the
object of your site fully last full
fully committed to
to getting more of it and then you
develop context of its circumstantial
nature against
everything else that you haven't seen
and you could have not seen
and you won't see immediately there is
already like a buffer zone between you
and that
gratuitous absorption with the scent
objects
okay yeah i've seen it and it's great
but did i have saying it's arising did i
say that scene did i have seen how that
thing manifested or whatever no
you were just subjected to all of these
things yet you took them as if you were
in control you were the owner you were
the kind of you hold the reins of it
but you don't you don't hold the reigns
even in regard to your own senses
let alone that which comes through your
senses to you
the sense objects the idea that there's
so many more things to see
yeah so many more things i could see
well that's the thing isn't that
wonderful that that thought would be on the level
that that thought would be on the level
of you are still absorbed in the content
of your singing
because if you actually develop the
context of everything
else that hasn't been seen is greater
the thought of all of the other things i
would see wouldn't matter in its content
because you would see it doesn't matter
what i see in the future it's always
going to be secondary to the framework
of everything else not seen
so if you do last for everything the new
things you could see means you have lost
the sight of the framework
you have basically obscured the context
because it doesn't matter what you see
it doesn't matter how many things you
see how many times you see it by being seen
how many times you see it by being seen
becomes second seeing it makes it second
and then you realize
oh so there is no way for me to access
it without seeing it
with the lust so if i want to act out of
lust i have to make myself second to this by
i have to make myself second to this by
acting out of lust
you put the second as first you put the
particular things that circumstantially
have been seen you make that the center
of your experience and your action and
your choices
which means you then become dependent
upon that which is already second
and that's the similarity of the manual
says chasing after sense objects
it's like climbing the tree to eat the
mangoes at the top
and then somebody comes who can't climb
the tree but he can cut the tree
so when he starts cutting the tree like
he's not cutting you
he's not attacking you with the axe but
he's removing that upon which you stand
those sense objects that you're
currently committed to and unless you
quickly withdraw yourself from the sense
objects i
quickly come down the tree you will
suffer death or deadly suffering
so if you have lust means you have
already perverted a picture you've
already put the second is first and
first the second
first is everything else not seen first
is the circumstantial nature of scene
if you maintain that doesn't matter what
future seeing what possibility of future
seeing it will all have to come second to the
it will all have to come second to the
framework of everything else not seen
and that's exactly how you develop your
mind above lust
you don't develop your mind above love
by never perceiving anything
beautiful in the world you develop your
mind above lust by not being able to
pervert that order ever again
in the world it doesn't matter what you
see so yeah what is
what what is uh much more non-lust
yeah from that point of view you realize
that the basically the absence of lust
is greatest and that's why it is
possible to overcome centrality as
as kind of hard as it is it's still
possible because it's fundamentally
second if sensuality were truly rooted in
if sensuality were truly rooted in
things you see
and the way you see them it would be
impossible and it wouldn't be a problem
then you wouldn't need to free yourself
from it but the reason why sensuality is
a problem because it requires that
perversion of that perception
it requires distortion it requires the
wrong view
it requires implicit risk
of committing to that which is
circumstantial
i mean like imagine somebody offers you
you know here's a card for you drive it
for free brand new car keys
no driven by the way you might have a
bomb rig to it
it might go off it might not go off
would you risk it
would you risk it even even even
touching the the the door handle
no no i'd rather walk thank you very
much oh here is a drink enjoy it it's it's
oh here is a drink enjoy it it's it's
it's it's it's beautiful in every
garden it might be poisonous by the way
so you wouldn't do it then because see
doesn't matter the appeal of the sense
object how much you lasted for this type of car
how much you lasted for this type of car
or for that type of drink
now with the framework with the context
properly established
of oh this is basically establishing
your own
core upon something utterly
circumstantial that when it changes it's not if it's
that when it changes it's not if it's
when it changes
you will you cannot remain unaffected by
that
so maintaining that context doesn't
matter what comes in your field of
vision you will not have lust towards it
you will not have lust towards it
because the paddle will be apparent the
danger becomes apparent as we would say
you lose sight of that well it's
mutually exclusive you can't have the
context of the
the danger the risk the circumstantial
nature and enjoy the object of that which is
and enjoy the object of that which is
circumstantial and risky
the only way to enjoy it is to not see
the risk
no matter what i i haven't seen if i see
it it's not exactly
it's not like i must never see like you
will not seek things out but if they do
arise you will not be
overwhelmed or afraid of trying to avoid
it either
so in the scene they will just be the
scene there will be no avoiding it or or
there will be no avoiding it or or
trying to prolong nothing
just in the scene there's just the scene
because in the scene there is no more
perversion of the context of the scene
that's adverse yeah that the buddhist
then gives
mulunkia footer instructions how to
train and i'll just read it out quickly
and i'll just read it out quickly
there's obviously so many different
translations sure says when regarding
sure says when regarding
things seeing heard sensed and cognized
by you
in the scene there will be merely the
scene in the herd there will be merely the
in the herd there will be merely the
herd in a sense there will be merely
the sense and the cognitive merely
recognized then you will not be by that
then you will not be by that
that by which you defined you won't be
basically you want that's what means
like when you establish your being
upon that last towards the scene it
defines you
as i said your ownership things you are
committed to emotionally
things you you crave for things you want
to have things you want to protect
having and so on
that is what defines you that is what
your sense of self is
and there's that suit that says that
basically say he was defined by his
possession say if that king wouldn't
have the king's
horses king's wives kings palaces king's
army would he be the king
could he act as a king no
but because he has these things that's
why he is the king
but in the mind that is already
perverted with this lust
you think you are the king first and
that's that that the most fundamental
that that the most fundamental
distortion that does
you think things are yours because you
are it's actually the other way around you
it's actually the other way around you
are you have a sense of self
for whatever it is because you keep
owning things gratuitously and you keep
owning them because you don't see them
as circumstantial
you don't see them as subject to change
so even when the change happens
blatantly in your face you you don't see
that as a relevant
symptom or that undermines your
ownership because you assumed yourself
to come first
so you then just isolate these examples
when change goes against you
and undermines your ownership and
undermines your sense of self and then
just try to cover it up with other
things getting the new property and new
getting the new property and new
ownership and new possessions
that's where sensuality basically a form
of owning and consumption
is the only way the petition knows how
to deal with any
discomfort emotionally that he
experiences he doesn't know how to
escape the painful feeling
in any other world in any other way
except turning towards centrality
and trying to basically cover it up with
new stuff
the fact is that things could change
against their will
means that fundamentally they cannot be
owned even if you are owning them owning
them now
it's not the ownership that you assume
you have
which is the ownership of control and
mastery of these things so when you see
the circumstantial nature of this by
dwelling that basically that
circumstantial context you will
be unable to not include yourself in it
as well
you're going to start feeling it in
other words so you start contemplating
the circumstantial nature of your
possessions and sooner or later you're
gonna feel a pang
of of dukkha basically when you touch
upon something that's dear to you
and now you start contemplating it as
publishable and then it's just oh so then you
and then it's just oh so then you
yourself
are equally subject to these things i
mean the body is the closest
well the body is the closest yeah but
it's also the hardest one to see because
through the body you get the pleasure
upon which you you develop yourself as
dependent upon the sense objects so
you don't even see the body correctly in
other words even when people say yes the
body is a nietzsche
unless you feel anxiety and fear on
account of it you're not doing it
rightly you're not seeing the nature of the book
you're not seeing the nature of the book
or you might be an arrogant
but again you wouldn't be listening
these instructions if you were
so more like here no so that's the point
you your sense of self your sense of
everything basically
ownerships and views and everything it's
because you possess
things first it's because
every single individual time you engage
with the objects of your senses
you do so ignorantly you do so without
the right context
you do so without maintaining the
recognition that they're
circumstantial throughout not in the
beginning but now it's final
in the beginning in the middle in the
end doesn't matter what point what point
you engage with things
they remain in the nature in the core
circumstantial anichia
fundamentally you give possessions by
correcting the distortion
that these possessions have that the
last towards the possession
have basically maintained
so in the scene there's just a scene
there's no distortion
clear
but for somebody without the right
context in the scene well there is lust there is
in the scene well there is lust there is
sense of self
there is ownership that is basically
perception of permanence is everything
just in the scene
yeah exactly so they are defined by the
scene or they are in the scene or they are
or they are in the scene or they are
different from the same either way
there's all this mass caused by lust
towards the scene
not by the scene by the way when you are
not by that then you will not be there
by that then you will not be there
in yeah that's basically depend uh
living in
pretty much seeing yourself as um
in the same world of all these objects
that you own that's just proliferation
of that self view
because it's it it can kind of grow
infinitely proliferated
so through only through being defined by
pretty much objects of your senses by
things you see
smell taste touch by chasing the
pleasure of these things
you become a being that's in the world
of these sense objects
and that's right a thought of sense
restraint a thought of not chasing the central
a thought of not chasing the central
pleasure
first and if like in the beginning if
the mind is not trained
will fill you with anxiety and terror
this will kill me
this will kill the level of me that i
proliferated to
and that's what the same people like
even people who are not into practice
when they get like they chase sensuality
to the point of basically
if you don't meet the required threshold
of engagement with your sense objects
you start experiencing basically
very painful psychological states
loss of existence yeah exactly like
vacuuming and dread and fear and all
this and then you quickly need to find
and then you quickly need to find
activities and things to do and things
to keep yourself occupied
but then equally if you actually are
able to not
kind of give in to that anxiety and be
overwhelmed by it
and endure it and refuse to engage with
the sense object to the same extent
you are diminishing that protrudes the
proliferated being
in that world of sense objects and you
can do so by maintaining the context of
the circumstantial nature towards things
you want to engage with
because that's another thing if you were
oh i have all this i need to do this i
need to do this
if you reestablish the context of
circumstantial nature even of the
possibilities of things you could do
you already lost the last of what's
doing that and then you'll end up just
doing things you have to do things that
are practical in nature that are
required whatever you wouldn't be doing them out
whatever you wouldn't be doing them out
of lust in other words
that verse continues when you are not
therein then you will be neither here
nor beyond nor in between the two
this itself is the end of suffering
so that's the instruction to malanke and
then mulanki says to the buddha i understand
mulanki says to the buddha i understand
in detail
principle sir the meaning of what was
stated by the blessed one in brief
and this is his verse which is also
found in the taragata
having seen a form with mindfulness
confused attending to the pleasing sign
having seen the form with context
confused with recollected yes
without the right context with other
right recollectiveness having seen the
form without a context
you will be confused with it like you're
already putting it first
as opposed to second you're not seeing
that you'll be attending to the pleasing
sign yeah it means you're already pulled by
yeah it means you're already pulled by
pleasure
and the only as i said in the beginning
of this talk the way to not be public
pleasure is not to never see things
but to never lose the context because
context means recognition the right
order if there is already lust means there is
if there is already lust means there is
absence of conflict
you always start with lust you always
start with perversion it's a mode of
being so it takes effort of going against that
so it takes effort of going against that
grain to develop the right context and
then yeah sure the point will come will
be a matter of choice
of a clearer kind where you can clearly
see mindfulness of last or last and one
mindfulness of last or last and one
experiences it with an infatuated mind
yeah and remains holding to it yeah
assuming it
assuming it in that wrong order
and many feelings grow
yeah originating from that science so
i mean like you you your mode of being
becomes dependent upon the site sound
smell taste touches which means now
everything you start ex feeling
experiencing feelings on account of it
is now on top of that so you're just
proliferating more and more
that's what like every you know any
central basically if there is no if
sensuality is not kept in check
for most people by circumstances or by
limited access to it
everybody would be an addict
and most people are one way or the other
so that's what i mean like it's not a
static thing
okay i'll just enjoy centrality and then
i'll restrain myself enough each time
you enjoy sensuality
means next time you'll need to enjoy
more of it your being grows towards it
you're becoming more dependent about it
upon it it's not a static thing
and that's the danger you have to
recognize as well when people think
okay now i understand this i'll restrain
later later might be too late as it might be
later might be too late as it might be
too much
you only have maybe a certain limited of
capacity to withdraw yourself from it and if you
to withdraw yourself from it and if you
overflow that being of sensuality you
will not have means of basically digging
yourself out of it anymore
you became too dependent
so many feelings grow originating from
that sight
covetousness and annoyance as well by
which one's mind
becomes disturbed for one who
accumulates suffering
like this is said to be far forward
yeah you just cut more and more and more
just piling things up
and then even when people who a person
with all that
piled up on him thinks about ibana he
will think it
in terms of that power basically for him
nibana will be another central thing the
greatest fulfillment of desire the greatest bliss
fulfillment of desire the greatest bliss
the greatest pleasure which is just the
extension of
everything else he's been chasing so far
so that's what i mean like when i said
before nibana is closer to death for a petuna
nibana is closer to death for a petuna
then basically that which he thinks
nibbana is
and that's why again many numerous times
in the suttas
when the buddha would talk to lay people
some of them
would ask and he would give them the
description of anibana in his
and they would go completely distraught
absolute breakdown mental breakdown fall
on the ground
agony pulling things like oh that will
kill me that will destroy me
that liberation is the death of me
because it is
it's the death of your sense of self i
proliferated being upon sense objects
feelings on accountability cravings and
so on assumptions of course
and yeah that's why the true practice is
more practically speaking more often
than not it will be unpleasant for
people certainly in the beginning
because it's going to be about undoing
your sense of self
not finding that last missing bit that
will make you fallen
and completed into this ultimate joy of
nirvana no no it's undoing that whole
stinky pile of sensual rubbish
and the more you accumulate the more
work you have to basically do to clean
it up
so that's the the carelessness you know
it was about carelessness it's basically
fundamentally procrastination
like people who read the suttas
recognize what needs to be done
but then keep sort of absorbing
themselves from the sense of duty to do
it
or or kind of postponing it or later
wait for the right condition
whatever it is wait for this you're just
procrastinating which means it's not a
static thing
so your procrastination for as long as
it lasts
results in accumulation of more things
for that period of time that you then
have to clean it
so you couldn't make yourself clean your
room when it was barely cluttered
because you were procrastinating now
because of your procrastination you have
100 times
more things to clean good luck starting
now
so the burden accumulates because that's
been your practice
yeah that's been your model being
when recollected when you have that
context mindfulness one sees a form one is not
mindfulness one sees a form one is not
inflamed by lust for that sight
one experiences it with a dispassionate
mind and does not remain holding
one lives recollected mindful in such a
way that even as one sees the form and while
that even as one sees the form and while
one undergoes a feeling
suffering is diminished not built up
because there's no craving that's being
basically cultivated towards it
and for one you prioritize the context
not the content
of your experience fundamentally that's
what it is
yeah and for one dismantling suffering
like that
nabani is said to be close by exactly
he's already
peeling off all these layers
like a skilled butcher cutting up a cup
the cap
cleaning and cleaning and cleaning
polishing polishing
because that's the thing even like even
almost like a mundane level of practice
you know i don't know somebody you see
somebody and it's upsetting to you
or you see somebody and you're infected
with lust doesn't matter
the point is the context is there is a
lustful mind
the context is there is an angry mind
doesn't matter who it is
the content of that experience is the
person you're angry with or the person
you're lost with the words
so you always have a choice that means
sensory strength fundamentally is done
blindly but it actually the reason why
it's necessary and why it's wholesome
because it emulates the nibana
absence of sensuality is what nibana is
absence of possibility of lust is what
hibana is
and that is basically outlined through
sense restraint
now of course you need to develop
understanding through that sense
restraint but without unders without sensory
but without unders without sensory
strain there is no place for
understanding to
to occur so even on that mundane level
you have a choice whether to
like leap into the content of your
experience and he is the reason of my anger or
and he is the reason of my anger or
think about him
because you are angry or abstain from
giving into that pool
to that burden that's kind of weighing
on you to go that way
and stay on the level of the context
which is
angry mind endures
if you lapse from the context you find
yourself thinking about the person
you're angry
with you re-establish the context anger
is there i don't care on account of what
you're already not particularly acting
towards craving and feeling and aversion
towards person you hate
same with the lust lustful mind is there
circumstantial well by staying on the level of the
well by staying on the level of the
context the circumstantial nature of
that basically person that made you angry
basically person that made you angry
becomes apparent because then you also
realize yeah i was angry yesterday with somebody
yeah i was angry yesterday with somebody
else so
anger is not solely confined to this
face although that's how it seems when
it's present no it's just it's him
no anger is first not that which made
you angry seemingly
again putting the second as the first as
the basis as the root of your anger
no the angry mind is the first
not that which you've seen that made you
angry that's always the second because
you've seen it
so same like lustful thoughts angry
thoughts whatever it is but it's pulling towards
whatever it is but it's pulling towards
pulling away you want to have it you
want to destroy it you want to kill it
you want to possess it
all of that is engagement with the
content at the expense of the context you can't
at the expense of the context you can't
have it both you can't be mindful
as in have the right context and engage
in centrality it's mutually exclusive
practically speaking even on the most
mundane level of practice
every single time you have a possibility
to make the right choice
to restrain and stay on the level of the
context and endure it
if it's painful which it will be
or to sort of jump into the content
and then psychologize and whatever else
and you know
deal with it or more feel more and deal
with your feelings all of that is
secondary to you making the wrong choice
already choice
that basically reinforced the already
existing perversion of putting first
a second and second is first